<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The rich man's bounty, the true measure of his wisdom a sermon preached before the Lord Mayor, and Court of Aldermen, and citizens of London, at St. Brides Church, Easter-Wednesday, March 27, 1695 / by John Mapletoft ...</title>
            <author>Mapletoft, John, 1631-1721.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 58 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51879</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M563</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6441</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12636898</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12636898</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64900</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51879)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64900)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 697:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The rich man's bounty, the true measure of his wisdom a sermon preached before the Lord Mayor, and Court of Aldermen, and citizens of London, at St. Brides Church, Easter-Wednesday, March 27, 1695 / by John Mapletoft ...</title>
                  <author>Mapletoft, John, 1631-1721.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Brabazon Aylmer ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1]-[2] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Luke XII, 21 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Easter --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64900:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64900:1"/>
            <p>The <hi>RICH MAN</hi>'s Bounty, the True Meaſure of His Wiſdom.</p>
            <p>A SERMON Preached before the LORD MAYOR, AND <hi>Court of Aldermen,</hi> AND CITIZENS of <hi>LONDON:</hi> AT St. <hi>Brides Church,</hi> Eaſter-Wedneſday, <hi>March,</hi> 27. 1695.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Iohn Mapletoft,</hi> D.D. Vicar of St. <hi>Lawrence-Jury.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</p>
               <bibl>Demophil.</bibl>
               <p>He is a Wiſe Man, and Dear to God, who takes as much Care for his Soul, as others do for their Bodies.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Brabazon Aylmer</hi> at the Three Pigeons againſt the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> 1695.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:64900:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:64900:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>LUKE, Xii.</hi> Ver. <hi>21.</hi> So is he that layeth up Treaſure for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and is not Rich towards God.</head>
            <p>THeſe Words are the Reſult, and Concluſion of a Parable ſpoken by our Bleſſed Lord: The Occaſion of which was this. One of his Hearers had Interrupted him, whileſt he was diſcourſing about ſome of the great Duties and Rewards of our H. Religion, with a Requeſt, that he would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide a difference between him and his Brother, about an Eſtate fallen to them in common: This our Lord refuſeth to do. Man, ſaith he, <hi>ver.</hi> 14. <hi>Who made me a Judge or a Divider over you?</hi> For, coming upon bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs of a much greater importance, he would not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage himſelf in theſe leſſer matters. But from hence he takes occaſion to Caution his Followers, againſt ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their Hearts too much upon tranſitory things; and he ſaid unto them, <hi>Take heed and beware of Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>i. e.</hi> of having and deſire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more than you need, or more than you ought to have: For by Covetouſneſs, Chriſt here plainly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, and forbids ſuch an over-eager deſire of, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication to the getting, or keeping Wealth as is incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with Juſtice or Charity; that care we ought to take of our poor Brethren out of Love to God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:64900:3"/>all things, and a ſettled Reſolution to pleaſe him in diſpoſal of our Riches. The Nature, Folly, and Danger of which Crying Sin, our Lord ſets forth and repreſents for our Inſtruction, in this following Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. A Rich Man in a very Plentiful Year, being at a loſs where to beſtow all his Increaſe, reſolves to pull down his Barns, and to build much Larger. And when all his Goods were ſafely layd up, he means to ſpend the reſt of his Life in Eaſe and Pleaſure; to enjoy all he hath himſelf alone, without any regard to the needs of others, and without making any Reflection, whence that Plenty came, for what end it was ſend him, or what account he was to make for it. <hi>Soul,</hi> ſaith he <hi>ver.</hi> 19. <hi>Thou haſt much Goods layd up for many Tears, take thine Eaſe, Eat, Drink and be merry, or Feaſt.</hi> We have here the Uncharitable Rich Mans Character: He is laying up Treaſure for himſelf only, without any conſideration either of God or Man. His Eſtate is all his own, and he, or his will enjoy it all themſelves. He knows no happineſs, nor deſires any other, ſave only what his Wealth can procure him: And as for the Poor, God can provide for them without his help. Now in the next words, the Folly and Diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the Miſery and Ruine of this poor Inconſiderate Senſual Wretch, are expoſed by our Saviour for a warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to others. But God ſaid unto him, <hi>Thou Fool, this night thy Soul ſhall be required of thee; then whoſe ſhall thoſe things be which thou haſt provided?</hi> Thoſe many Years he promiſed himſelf, are at an end in one night; the goods he reckons upon are no longer his; and he is called to give an account of the abuſe of his Truſt; and muſt expect the ſad doom of an Unjuſt Steward, who had either Riotouſly waſted, or Covetouſly hoar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded up for himſelf, what his Lord put into his hands
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:64900:3"/>for the Maintenance and Relief of his Fellow-Servants. <hi>So is he, ſaith our Lord, that layeth up Treaſure for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and is not Rich towards God.</hi> Such is he in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign and practiſe, and ſuch is the iſſue of his ill-natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red folly; <hi>ſo</hi> very Fooliſh, <hi>ſo</hi> wholly Diſappointed, and Miſerable is that Man, who is more concern'd about getting or keeping an Eſtate, than about employing a good part of it in Works of Mercy.</p>
            <p>Having thus ſet this Text in its true light, and ſhewn its coherence with, and relation to, the foregoing Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept and Parable of our Lord; and that it is the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the one, and the Moral of the other. I ſhall uſe this Method in my diſcourſe thereon.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. I ſhall a little more fully explain and enlarge up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on its true ſenſe and meaning.</item>
               <item>2. I ſhall propound to your view and conſideration that General Doctrine which ſeems to be the main Scope and Deſign of the whole, and make good the truth of it by proper Arguments.</item>
               <item>3. I ſhall make ſome Reflections pertinent to this matter.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Then as to the meaning of the phraſes here uſed, <hi>Laying up treaſure for a mans ſelf,</hi> evidently im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports his getting, or keeping, or uſing ſuperfluous wealth; what is over and above either the neceſſities, or true natural, (not fantaſtical imaginary) cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences of life, only for himſelf, or his own neareſt Relations; or to gratify any inordinate appetites, ſuch as are the too great love of mony, or of ſenſual plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, or vain-glorious pride; and this without taking notice of, and relieving the wants of other men. And, on the contrary, <hi>to be rich towards God,</hi> implys our having a due regard to his will and Laws in the get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and managing our wealth, and behaving our
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:64900:4"/>ſelves as STEWARDS, not as LORDS, and abſolute Proprietors of thoſe gifts we receive from GOD. So that, if we joyn both theſe expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions together, to <hi>Lay up Treaſure for our ſelves, and not to be RICH towards GOD,</hi> will ſignify, both from the force of the words, and the whole Scope of the Parable, ſo to get, or keep, or uſe wealth, as not to have due reſpect to Almighty God, as to the Supream giver of diſpoſer of it; and to that end for which it was lent us, and the uſe we ought to put ſome good part of that to, of which we have no true need our ſelves; or to place our chief Happineſs in our Riches, <hi>Soul, take thine eaſe;</hi> or in thoſe bodily, bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-Animal Pleaſures to which they chiefly Miniſter; or thoſe empty Titles, Preference, or other Worldly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages they uſually procure, ſo as not to employ what we have to ſpare, at leaſt, a very conſiderable part of a large Income, in ſupplying the wants of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and Induſtrious Poor. All this is apparently imply'd in that prepoſterous care, and perverſe miſ-manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of riches here condemned by our Lord under the name of laying up Treaſure for our ſelves, and not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rich towards God. And the word <hi>So,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>necting this <hi>verſe</hi> to the preceding parable, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying it to the whole Scheme by way of Accomoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Reſemblance, gives us this general ſenſe, as the drift and purport of our Lords diſcourſe on this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject: Conſider how groſs the folly, how unreaſonable the procedure, and how certain, and withal, how ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible the defeat of ſuch a Rich Man's hope muſt ſoon be, who had no conſideration for other mens needs, no end, no God but himſelf, when he is ſurpriz'd by death; and then, Take heed and beware of ſuch Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs, and irregular ſelf-love as is here Exempli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy'd:
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:64900:4"/>Of hoarding up for your ſelves what God entruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you with for the ſupport, and comfort of his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. <hi>So is he, i. e.</hi> ſuch a ſhort-ſighted unthinking fool, as this here in the Parable: <hi>So</hi> unmindful of God his great Maſter and Benefactor; <hi>So</hi> inhuman and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardleſs of his poor BRETHREN, who periſh for want of thoſe proviſions which his barns could not hold, and might have ſaved him the labour of build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing new ones; and <hi>So</hi> miſerably diſappointed at the laſt; and <hi>So</hi> loſt and <hi>So</hi> undone for ever is that wretched man, who ſpends all his time, and care, and ſtrength in increaſing, or preſerving his wealth; or abuſes it to Luxury, or to pride and vanity, without taking care <hi>To be Rich towards God,</hi> or to lay out a good propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his abundance in thoſe works of mercy which God doth require of him in this, and will reward him for in the next life. So much for the Explication and Meaning of the Words.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The general Doctrine deducible from this Parable, as the main drift and deſign of it ſeems to be this; That, as it is too much the Cuſtom, ſo it is both the mighty folly, and error, the diſappointment and the ruin of too many Rich men, that they are more intent upon adding to their heap, and keeping it together; or in laviſhing out their ſtore unduly upon themſelves; or on too carefully laying it up for their poſterity, than upon managing their great affluence ſo as may turn to their beſt account in the next life; and may moſt comply with that end, for which this Talent was put into their hands. Or, that he is extreamly fooliſh who ſets his heart more upon leaving a great Eſtate at his death, than upon doing a great deal of good with it in his life time. And on the other ſide, the rich man's diligent ſtudy and practiſe of Beneficence and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:64900:5"/>Charity, is the true meaſure of his Wiſdom, as well as the proper duty of his place and ſtation.</p>
            <p>Now the truth of this Doctrin will manifeſtly appear from theſe four following conſiderations. They are extreamly fooliſh, and like to him her mentioned, who <hi>Lay up Treaſure for themſelves, and are not Rich towards God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe all thoſe who thirſt after wealth immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately, or uſe great portions of it in the ſervice of any vice, miſtake the nature and end of Riches.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe they underſtand not the true uſe and mighty advantage which may be made of them, when they are employ'd ſo as they ought to be.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Becauſe by neglecting, or coming ſhort in their works of mercy, they deprive themſelves of the chief, or only Remedy againſt the certain danger and uſual miſchief of Worldly proſperity, and ſo make it hard for themſelves to be ſaved.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Becauſe as their Riches make it hard, ſo their ill, or no uſe of them, and total want of Charity make it impoſſible for them to be ſaved, if they die in that ſtate.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They who are wholly taken up with the care and thoughts of mony, and over joy'd with great poſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, are very unwiſe, becauſe they are much miſtaken in the nature and value, &amp; power, and end of that which they make their Capital, their chief Affair. For they falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuppoſe that a great deal of wealth will furniſh all that is needful to make them truly Happy. But now the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Aſſertion to this too Fatal Error, is laid down by our Bleſſed Lord as the very reaſon why we ought to take heed and beware of Covetouſneſs, or a deſire of having too much, all we can get any way; for, ſaith he, <hi>A Mans life conſiſteth not in the abundance of the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:64900:5"/>things which he poſſeſſeth,</hi> i. e. No Mans life can be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prolonged one moment, or made more truly hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py by ſuch a ſurpluſage of riches as neither the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities, nor true Conveniences of life demand.</p>
            <p>All happineſs pretended to beyond this Compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency, either in the bare poſſeſſing, or in Luxuriouſly and vainly expending much wealth, is but a diſeaſed fancy and illuſion of brain-ſick men. And 'tis well known that all ſuch falſe Appetites and Ill-grounded deſires are as unſatiable, as they are unnatural, and unreaſonable. Neither the wealthieſt Prince that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was, nor the greateſt Conqueror, had every Gold, or Empire enough to make him eaſy and contented, as long as there was ſtill any more in the world.</p>
            <p>And no man can be happy who is not pleaſed with his preſent condition.</p>
            <p>But beſides this, Riches can neither make a man Wiſe nor Good: which is the proper felicity of rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal, intelligent beings. They riſe no higher than to provide for, and gratify the body which is the husk and ſhell only, or the priſon, as ſome call it, of that immortal ſpirit, which diſtinguiſhes us from the brute Beaſts; and ſo muſt raiſe us to another kind, and pitch of Happineſs than what we can have in Common with them.</p>
            <p>And this made <hi>Socrates</hi> ſuſpend his judgment con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the happineſs of the great King, or <hi>Perſian Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch,</hi> till he was better inform'd, how much Wiſdom and Vertue he had. And for the ſame reaſon, he refuſed to ſay, that another newly made a mighty rich man was happy, until he ſaw what uſe he would make of his Eſtate. For by theſe he rightly meaſured the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity of every man; and affirm'd, that all other things which miſ-judging vulgar minds dote on, Riches, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:64900:6"/>Honours, and Kingdoms, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> had no great matter in them, were of no Conſequence at all in order to make men happy. And a very Knowing Man of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (Lord <hi>Verulam</hi>) aſſures us, as well from his own, as from the Univerſal experience of Mankind, That Great Perſons muſt borrow other Mens opinions to think themſelves Happy: For if they judge by what they feel only, they cannot find any ſuch thing.</p>
            <p>Thus are theſe fond Admirers of Riches altogether ignorant of the true Nature and Power, or indeed, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potency, Inability of Wealth, to procure and to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh any happineſs to Man; and conſequently they are miſerably fool d and abus'd in a Falſe expectation of what it can never perform. Since no Solid Rational ſatisfaction of the mind of Man ever was, or can be ever found, either in thoſe low deſpicable Pleaſures of Senſe, in which the Bruits, or rival, or perhaps excel Man; or in all the Pageantry of Secular Greatneſs, the empty Smoke, Duſt and Noiſe of Worldly Pomps and Vanities; to which only, abundance always can, and commonly doth exalt, and then abuſe and puſſ up thoſe weak untaught minds who know no better things.</p>
            <p>Nor do theſe Men much reflect upon the fleeting fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Nature of theſe Tranſitory things; the great un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty there is of their poſſeſſing them one Day; <hi>Thou Fool,</hi> may God ſay to every one of them, <hi>this night thy Soul ſhall be required of thee:</hi> Nor upon the as great certainty that they can not long enjoy, what is the only Good they care to have.</p>
            <p>But now, he who underſtands the true nature of theſe things, and is too diſcerning to be brought by ſuch thin appearances of Happineſs into the common Paradiſe of Fools, looks upon a mighty Revenue, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as a great Burthen and Incumbrance, a thought<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64900:6"/>careful Province, and a Buſy Steward-ſhip.</p>
            <p>And all that can make it, I ſay not deſirable or va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luable, but tolerable to ſuch a man, is the hopes he hath by his wiſe management of his ten Tallents to bring Honour to his Great Maſter, and obtain the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward promiſed to the good and faithful Servant. His being a Large Diſpencer, and Inſtrument of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Bounty to the Family of God, is both the joy and ſupport of his Spirit, and the only true advantage of his having more then he needs, or would otherwiſe have the trouble of, if it were to be miſpent in the too generally received methods of the World.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Second,</hi> The Folly of thoſe who are more intent up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on laying up Treaſures on Earth than in Heaven, or up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on having a great Eſtate, than making a due and good uſe of what they have, is ſeen in this; that they do not conſider enough, nor underſtand what the beſt and true uſe of Wealth is, and how it may be moſt improved. It were eaſie for God ſo to order things here below, that no Man ſhould need to be Poor; but the Poor and Rich have from this variety and difference of their outward circumſtances, opportunity of exerciſing ſeveral Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Virtues which could not otherwiſe ſubſiſt and have place amongſt Men. The Pious and Induſtrious Poor, have hereby occaſion to exerciſe their Patience and Submiſſion to the Will of God, and their depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence on, and truſt in him for a ſupply to their wants. And the Rich have manifold invitations and oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities to ſhew the ſincerity of their love to God, and to their Brethren, by their Liberality; as alſo to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs their thankfulneſs to God for theſe outward Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, and that he has put them into that more happy ſtation of being Givers rather than Receivers; and hereby to own that as all they have is from God, ſo it
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:64900:7"/>ought to be managed with regard to his will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and for his greater Glory.</p>
            <p>Beneficence alſo gives us a peculiar Title to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and Bleſſing, and Protection of God here in this Life; nay, even to more Wealth, if God ſees it to be beſt for us.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Hierom</hi> affirms, that he did not remember to have read, that any Perſon ever had died an ill Death, who had been a great Alms-giver in his Life time. And we read, <hi>Prov.</hi> 11.24, 25. <hi>There is that ſcattereth, and yet increaſeth; and there is that withholdeth more than is meet, but it tendeth to Poverty. The Liberal Soul ſhall be made fat, and he that watereth, ſhall be water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed alſo himſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But as a large diffuſive Charity, and imparting to others in a good proportion to what Abundance God hath bleſſed us with, is the proper uſe of a great In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, ſo is it the beſt improvement we can poſſibly make of it; this is here ſtyled, <hi>Being Rich towards God,</hi> and by our Lord, <hi>Laying up for our ſelves Treaſure in Heaven,</hi> Mat. 6.20. or having Treaſure in Heaven. 'Tis putting ſo much ſtock into the Hands of God to be there Secured and Improv'd for us and ours, upon the beſt aſſurance, even his own Word, of having ſo much of it repaid to us again, or to ours in this World, as God knows to be beſt for us or them. <hi>Prov.</hi> 19.17. <hi>He that hath pity upon the Poor, lendeth unto the Lord, and that which he hath given will he repay him again.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But above all, this is the certain, and perhaps the only way, for Rich Men both to ſecure to themſelves a Crown of Righteouſneſs thro' the Mercy of God in Chriſt, and to increaſe the Weight and Glory of that Crown in Gods Kingdom. Our Bleſſed Lord promiſes a Reward to him, who ſhall give a Cup of cold Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:64900:7"/>only, to any of his in the Name of a Diſciple, <hi>i. e.</hi> becauſe they belong to him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.24. And in that deſcription of the Day of Judgment, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. he is pleaſed to aſſign no other cauſe of his putting the Bleſſed of his Father into poſſeſſion of that Kingdom prepared for them from the Foundation of the World, but only their having Fed and Cloathed him when he Hungry and Naked, and taken him in when he was a Stranger, and viſited him when he was Sick and in Priſon; <hi>i. e.</hi> their having relieved and taken care of his Brethren in their Needs and Diſtreſſes, which he therefore interprets as if done to himſelf, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly rewards with everlaſting Happineſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Very Rich men, if they are not given to Charity, and that in a good proportion to their Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous Riches, are very fooliſh, becauſe by their failing in this duty, they neglect and deprive themſelves of the moſt efficacious, if not the only ſure remedy, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the danger and miſchief of worldly proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; And that great difficulty our Saviour has told us there is for them to enter into the Kingdom of God.</p>
            <p>'Tis either the too great love, and over value men have for Riches; their ſetting their heart upon them, pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing their confidence in them; or their abuſe of them, to the ſupport, and gratification of their Ambition and Pride, or their Senſuality; and their forgetfulneſs of God, which make it harder for a Rich Man, as Chriſt poſitively affirms, Mat. 19.24. <hi>To enter into the Kingdom of God, than it is for a</hi> Camel <hi>to go through the eye of a needle.</hi> And the only way that God takes, as far as we can know, to work this Miracle, for thoſe Rich Men who do enter into his Kingdom, or become true ſincere Chriſtians, is by infuſing this Grace of Charity into their Souls; whereby he makes
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:64900:8"/>them Willing and Deſirous to part with ſo much of their Wealth to the Poor, that they may have good Store of Treaſure laid up for them in Heaven; and by this means their hearts are looſed and diſ-entangled from theſe periſhing things, and centred upon God as their laſt end, and Supream Felicity.</p>
            <p>It was the want of this Spiritual Wiſdom, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to beneficence, which made that young man who gave occaſion to that hard and amazing ſaying, forſake Chriſt. He went away with a ſorrow propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable to the greatneſs of his wealth. <hi>He was very ſorrowful,</hi> Luk. 18.23. <hi>For he was very Rich.</hi> And he fondly choſe rather to part with all hopes of that Eternal Life he had been ſo earneſtly enquiring af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, than with the great poſſeſſions he was maſter of.</p>
            <p>Certainly did Rich Men conſider well the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible danger they are in, of being loſt forever upon account of their Riches, (if they will believe our LORD and MASTER,) they would never have St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s charge out of their mind, which he enjoyns <hi>Timothy</hi> to give them, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.17, 18. They would neither be high-minded, inſolent, or deſpiſers of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, only for having leſs mony than they have; nor truſt in their uncertain Riches, but in the living God; from whom they receive them, and whoſe Stewards they are. They would then make it their chief bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, their Trade or Calling, and look upon it as their greateſt concern, and true intereſt to do good to thoſe who need them, to be Rich in good Works; They would eſteem theſe the beſt and moſt valuable part of their wealth, becauſe they will be of uſe to them in the next life, and conſequently would be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to diſtribute and willing to communicate.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:64900:8"/>
            <p>The Apoſtle backs his Exhortation with this irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtible Argument to all who believe another world, <hi>viz.</hi> That Rich Men do hereby lay up in Store for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a good foundation againſt the time to come, that they may lay hold on Eternal Life. Since then a ſtudyed well-Proportioned bounty to the Poor, is the moſt ſure preſervative againſt thoſe deſtructive poyſons of Mens Souls, <hi>viz.</hi> Covetouſneſs, Pride, Lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ury, Intemperance of all ſorts; which are ſo often the ſucceſsful Temptations of Wealth, that only the wiſeſt and beſt Men (which are not always the greateſt number among the Rich,) are able to reſiſt them, it muſt needs be the worſt Husbandry, and the greateſt folly in the world not to lay out our mony upon ſo great advantage; and not ſtarve our own exceſſes, and irregular courſes, by making a plentiful proviſion for our neceſſitous brethren.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> The undoing folly and miſery of all Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable Rich Men, is palpably manifeſt in this, <hi>viz.</hi> That by ſuch unfaithfulneſs to their truſt, and inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity towards their brethren, they deſtroy all hopes of being Happy in the next State. Wealth, and that power, and intereſt which it uſually makes way for, and procures, are thoſe particular Talents which God hath committed to their management; and are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be carefully, and diligently improv'd by them, to his Honour, and their own Perſonal good, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage in the other world, by their feeding and cloathing, and relieving and aſſiſting all the diſtreſſed afflicted members of their Common Saviour. But now, if inſtead of giving their Lord's Houſhold meat in due ſeaſon, they ſhall be arrogant and injurious up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſtrength of their Riches; and ſhall Eat and Drink with the Drunken, if they ſhall ſpend in the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:64900:9"/>of their own Vices what they receiv'd for the benefit and uſe of their Fellow Servants, <hi>their Lord ſhall come in a day when they look not for him,</hi> Mat. 24.50. <hi>All ſhall cut them aſunder;</hi> (which was the puniſhment of falſe Knaves and Cheating Villains) and ſhall appoint them their Portion with the Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, where there ſhall be weeping and Gnaſhing of Teeth, <hi>i. e.</hi> in the endleſs Torments of Hell Fire. Thus now have I made good, I hope, that Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which I advanced as the general Scope of this Parable, <hi>viz.</hi> That 'tis a mighty folly, and will prove a terrible diſappointment at the laſt to all thoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderate men who are more concern'd to heap up Riches for themſelves, or their Children; or more for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to miſpend their wealth in any unjuſtifyable way of Sin or Vanity; than to employ their over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plus in ſuch works of Piety and Charity, as make for the Honour of God, and the ſuccour and relief of his Children, and Servants. Or, that he is the very Fool, here called ſo by God himſelf, who makes it more his aim and buſineſs to be a great, than a Good Man; and to be Rich and High in this World, than to be for ever happy in that which is to come.</p>
            <p>For, <hi>So is he; So</hi> is every one of theſe narrow Souls, theſe ſelf-ſeeking Rich Men; 1. <hi>So</hi> miſtaken in the nature of Wealth, and ſo abuſed in his Expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Happineſs; 2. <hi>So</hi> ignorant of its true and beſt uſe, and of the great advantage may be made by em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploying it ſo as it ought to be; 3. <hi>So</hi> negligent, and unwary in obviating, and preventing the danger which all Rich Men are in, and the harm and miſchief which moſt receive from too great Abundance; 4. <hi>So</hi> for ever ruin'd by the miſ-uſe of his Talent, is that man, <hi>who lays up Treaſure for himſelf, and is not
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:64900:9"/>Rich towards God. So</hi> Unwiſe, <hi>ſo</hi> Diſ-appointed, and <hi>ſo</hi> Finally Undone is that Miſerable Man, who having not made himſelf Friends of the Mammon of unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, (if not unjuſtly gotten, at leaſt too often unjuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly detained, or unjuſtly uſed, as well as) Fading, Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable, Periſhing Wealth, can have no juſt or good hopes that he ſhall ever be received into Everlaſting habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Gods Eternal Kingdom of Glory.</p>
            <p>Now if want of Beneficence, and of due proportions of Works of Mercy be the apparent Folly, and Sin, and Ruine of thoſe Rich Men who have no regard to Gods Laws, and the wants of others, in diſpoſing of their Eſtates; it hence follows, That a due care about, and a Conſciencious diſcharge of the obligation they have thereto, is the wiſdom and happineſs, of thoſe who uſe their Wealth to the glory of God, and the good of Men; or, that a Rich Man's well-proportioned Charity, is the beſt mark of his Prudence and Diſcretion.</p>
            <p>For ſome of the chief Properties and Rules of wiſdom are, I think, generally agreed to be theſe:</p>
            <p>Making a right Judgment of the Nature, and Intrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick Worth and Value of thoſe things we are concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to underſtand.</p>
            <p>Looking to the moſt diſtant iſſues and conſequents of them. A wiſe Man ſees as far before him as he can.</p>
            <p>Knowing how to make the true uſe and beſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement, or advantage of them to our ſelves.</p>
            <p>Being aware of, and avoiding all inconvenience or harm, we might otherwiſe come to ſuffer by, or from them.</p>
            <p>Propounding to our ſelves in general the Beſt and Nobleſt End, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Higheſt degree of Happineſs we are made capable of by our Nature, or the Favour of God.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:64900:10"/>
            <p>And then ſteadily purſuing this end by all requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite, moſt fit and proper ways, and means.</p>
            <p>Now he who makes it his main deſign, the affair and buſineſs of his Life, to <hi>be Rich towards God;</hi> to have his chief Treaſure in Heaven, and his Heart there alſo, even whilſt he is in this Earthly Tabernacle; he underſtands the nature &amp; properties of Wealth, and what he may, or may not expect from it. He knows how little will ſerve the needs of the Body, and furniſh all thoſe conveniences which a wiſe and good Man can think worth having: And that whatever is over and above this, hath no other good in it, ſave what ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes from our uſing it to the good of others. He rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kons ſo much only of his Eſtate to be properly his, as he either uſes himſelf, in complyance with the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt demands of Nature, and the dictates of ſober rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; or as he remits and ſends before him into that Heavenly Country and Houſe of his Father, towards which he is advancing every day, and where his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure will be of the greateſt benefit to him; <hi>That only is mine which I either make uſe of my ſelf,<note place="margin">Quello e mio che io godo, &amp; dono per Dio.</note> or give for Gods ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He prudently conſiders the few Moments he is to ſpend here as a point, as nothing, in compariſon with that eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal duration for which he is deſign'dand made; and that ſingle thought deſtroys and annihilates all thoſe falſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances of happineſs which either the groſs pleaſures of Senſe, or the thin air of Applauſe, or the noiſe of ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar State and Grandeur, which are uſually founded in &amp; ſupported by ſtore of Money, can any way pretend to.</p>
            <p>He judges of all theſe things as God doth (whoſe Judgment is the Rule and Standard of Truth) and who values Men by their true Wiſdom and Virtue, their Piety and Charity, their Meekneſs and Humility; not
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:64900:10"/>by their Birth, or Titles, or Riches, or any Quality which the weakeſt and worſt of Men may ſhare equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with the Beſt and the Wiſeſt.</p>
            <p>He knows that the only true uſe of very great Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence, is doing a very great deal of good to very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, to the Honour of God, and out of obedience to his Commands; that this is the higheſt improvement of periſhable goods, and the only way to change their nature, and make them durable for ever; ſince he will find the Rewards of his Charity, in an Endleſs ſtate of Felicity.</p>
            <p>His neither valuing himſelf upon his Riches, nor truſting in them; his Poverty of Spirit, his Humility and Contempt of the World, when he hath moſt of it; and parting with what others waſt in Pride and Lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, to Feed his poor Brother, ſecure him from the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of Wealth; He hath never any thing to ſpare for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Vice; and thus doth his Wealth make his way to Heaven more Eaſie and more Pleaſant too: Nor is Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty it ſelf ſo ſafe a Road thither, as Riches are to ſuch a Maſtering Mind.</p>
            <p>He propoſes to himſelf the Beſt and Nobleſt end, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Life, or the enjoyment of that Supreme Good, from whence he came, (and for, as well as by whom, he was made) to Eternal Ages. This he knows is the only true and proper, peculiar Happineſs of Immortal Spirits. He therefore values all things here below in proportion to their capacity, and tendency to ſerve him in order to his Great, his only Aim and Concern, to live with God for ever. To this end therefore, he will chiefly uſe his Wealth, and whatever Power or Intereſt that can give him.</p>
            <p>And whereas Riches too commonly make Men for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get both God and themſelves, they make this Wiſe Man
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:64900:11"/>more mindful of both; ſince he is always contriving how he may diſcharge his Truſt to his Lord, and how he may avoid thoſe Temptations and Snares into which they fall <hi>who will be Rich,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.9. who ſet their hearts upon getting Money, or place their Happineſs in it; who love the World, and the things of this World to that degree, as to ſtifle the Love of God in their Souls, and that regard they ought to have to his Law and Will.</p>
            <p>I ſhall conclude with a Reflection or two ariſing from, or pertinent to this matter.</p>
            <p n="1">1 If we deſire rather <hi>to be RICH towards GOD,</hi> than <hi>to lay up Treaſure for our ſelves, i. e.</hi> to exerciſe the Grace of Charity vigorouſly, in due meaſure, from right Principles, and moſt to our own advantage; we muſt endeavour to have our minds throughly poſſeſſed with, &amp; influenced by a ſincere hearty love to God. For on this our love to God above all things, we muſt found all that unfeigned affection, and good will we bear to Men, which will be a conſtant ſpur, and reſtleſs incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to all good offices they can need, and we perform.</p>
            <p>Our Bleſſed Lord having anſwered that Queſtion, <hi>Which is the great Commandment of the Law?</hi> Mat. 22. in theſe terms, <hi>Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thy Heart, and with all thy Soul, and with all thy Mind,</hi> adds of his own accord, and as a certain conſequent of the former, <hi>And the</hi> 2d. <hi>is like unto it, Thou ſhalt love thy Neighbour as thy ſelf.</hi> Now our Lord thus connect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe together, and making them joyntly the ſum of the Law and the Prophets; that in which they all conſpire, or the Abridgment, the whole of our duty; doth hereby evidently inſtruct us; That as the love and kindneſs we have for our Brethren is Inſeparable from that ſincere love we bear to God, ſo it muſt be ever
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:64900:11"/>grounded thereon. We muſt therefore love, be kind and helpful to all Men, becauſe we love that God whoſe Image they bear in common with our ſelves; whoſe Children they alſo are as well as we; who hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded us to love them as we do our ſelves, &amp; as he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved us, when he ſent his Son to be the Propitiation for our Sins, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.10, 11. and to reconcile us again to himſelf by his death on the Croſs. And if we do thus love our Brethren, we ſhall gladly take all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions to aſſiſt and relieve them, we ſhall be as forward to help them, as we deſire they ſhould be to help us, were we in the like diſtreſs.</p>
            <p>'Tis this, this inward affection, and hearty love to others, out of that Love and Duty we owe to God, which is both a Never-failing Spring, and the very Life and Soul of all External acts of Charity. And if this be wanting, tho' we ſhould beſtow all our goods to feed the Poor, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.3. if we were never ſo Boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful out of Vain-glory, or from any other Carnal Worldly conſideration, it would profit us nothing; it would be no diſcharge of our obligation, it would be of no account in the ſight of God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Since Works of Mercy are ſo much every Man's concern in his Station, and ſo much every Rich Mans, eſpecial, proper Duty, and mighty, indeed only ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, they muſt be a good part of every Rich Man's buſineſs too, of his thought, contrivance, and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al care. It were therefore very good and adviſeable, (if not neceſſary) that all Men, and particularly all Rich Men, ſhould ſeriouſly and attentively weigh and conſider with themſelves, what proportion of their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates it were fit for them to Allot and Conſecrate eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Year to Pious uſes, and to lay by ſuch a part as they reſolve on, out of every Sum they receive; which would
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:64900:12"/>have this good effect, among many others, that they would generally be ready for, and glad of all good oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions of diſtributing to the neceſſities of the Poor. And tho God hath given us no ſet Rule whereby to eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate this proportion, yet we may doubtleſs make one for our ſelves; in which our main care ought to be, that our Rule be not too narrow, that we do not too little. A defect here may prove our final undoing, whereas an Exceſs, if ſuch a thing can be imagined, would beſure to encreaſe our reward in the next life. A Learned and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary Divine of our Church (Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi>) in a Sermon Preach't upon this very occaſion before the then Lord Mayor and Aldermen of this City; obſerves, that every <hi>Jew</hi> (not the Rich only) was obliged (beſides ſeveral other ways of relieving the Poor mentioned in the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi>) to pay a Tenth part of all his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe or Income every Third Year, which is aequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent to one Thirtieth part every Year, to the uſe, and maintenance of the Poor, <hi>Deut.</hi> 14.28, 29. And this was Styled their Righteouſneſs, their neceſſary O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to the Law, and the loweſt degree of Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty among them: But the Good and Merciful Men, even of the <hi>Jews,</hi> were ſuch as did much out do what this Law exacted. Our Lord declares, That except <hi>our Righteouſneſs ſhall exceed the Righteouſneſs of the Scribes and Phariſees,</hi> (who practiſed ſuch external du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties doubtleſs at an higher rate than the common <hi>Jews</hi>) <hi>we ſhall in no caſe enter into the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> From all theſe premiſes, that Learned Man infers, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all colour of contradiction, that the proportion of the Chriſtian Alms-giver, to ſpeak at the leaſt, muſt be more than the Thirtieth part of his Yearly Revenue, or Increaſe. Now altho' it be true, that this Law gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the <hi>Jews,</hi> doth not oblige us Chriſtians in the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:64900:12"/>Letter of it, yet (as he well remarks) Gods Judgment to his People at that time, and in that State is worth our obſerving. But then we are here to remember, that every <hi>Jew,</hi> who had any Income or Increaſe, was ty'd to pay this Thirtieth part towards the maintenance of the Poor, even thoſe who had leaſt to ſpare; ſo that if Chriſtians in moderate circumſtances, who have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing to ſpare, are to exceed this Proportion, as hath been ſhewed; thoſe who are Rich, who have a great deal more than they need, muſt be worſe than <hi>Jews,</hi> if they make ſo low and ſcanty a Rule for their practiſe; for none who was accounted a Good or Merciful Man among them, contented himſelf with doing ſo little. Some conſiderate Perſons being in that mediocrity, or competency of theſe outward good things, that neither Poverty nor Riches, which was the Wiſe Man's choice, (and would be the choice of all Wiſe Men, if our Lords Judgment were throughly weighed and believed by them; ſince the Richer they are, the more hard ſtill it is for them to be ſaved) ſome of theſe ſober and ſerious Chriſtians, I ſay, have thought one Tenth part of their Yearly Revenue, or Annual Profits ariſing any other way, a Proportion low enough for them to beſtow in Works of Mercy. But Rich Men, and eſpecially thoſe who are very Rich, if they were very Wiſe too, will ſcarce ſtint themſelves, it is to be hoped, (in many circumſtances at leaſt) to a rate ſo diſ-proportionable to their abilitys. <hi>Zac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheus</hi>'s Example, who beſides reſtoring four ſold, if it ſhould appear that he had wronged any Man, gave half his goods to the Poor, is a much fitter Precedent for ſome of thoſe who have very great Eſtates, <hi>i. e.</hi> who have much more than they can ſpend every Year in ſuch ways as they will be able to anſwer for
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:64900:13"/>to God at the laſt day, that great day of Accounts. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly every Rich Man will do himſelf great right, in of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and ſeriouſly reflecting upon that Parable delivered by our Lord, <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.19. &amp;c. for his particular Cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and inſtruction. That Rich man there, hath nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther impiety, nor rapine, or injuſtice, nor any other flagrant Crime laid to his Charge: All we are told of him is, that he was Clothed in purple and fine linnen and fared ſumptuouſly every day; and that he did not feed the poor beggar with the crumbs which fell from his table, <hi>i. e.</hi> He lived very great, maintain'd his port, and quality in the world, indulg'd himſelf in the exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Luxury and Vanity, whilſt the poor ſtarv'd for want of that which his haughty Pride and Ryot made him think he needed for his own ſelf. And the next thing we hear of him, is, that he is dead and buried, and in Torments in Hell Fire.</p>
            <p>The learned <hi>Grotius</hi> asks this queſtion from the place, which I fear it will be hard for many Rich and Great Men ſatisfactorily to anſwer; <hi>Quomodo igitur poenam hanc diviti inflictam evadet pars magna Chriſtianorum?</hi> How, will ſo many Chriſtians, as imitate this Rich man's Example, be able to eſcape thoſe Torments in Hell to which he is doom'd? For tho' all the Alms in the world can never purchaſe Heaven (for Eternal Life is the gift of God thro' Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.23.) yet want of a competent, proportionable Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, alone, and without any other ſin? may prove, as ſure a way to loſe Heaven, as all the <hi>Atheiſm</hi> and Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, all the Lewdneſs and Wickedneſs any Man was ever guilty of.</p>
            <p>And ſince Chriſt gives no other reaſon of mens Condemnation at the day of judgment, but this only, (tho' others doubtleſs there will be) we cannot but
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:64900:13"/>conclude, that want of due Charity will be then, tho' not the only, yet to be ſure a very principal and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Article againſt thoſe forever unhappy men. And ſeeing that a narrow, ſlender, contracted Charity, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together diſproportionable to the Rich mans Abilities, will in all reaſon, be eſteemed by God as no Charity at all; All Rich men are as nearly concern'd to Study this point well, and to practiſe this duty with care and diligence, as they are not to periſh with their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and not to come into that place of Torments. And they ought therefore frequently to have in their thoughts that ſaying of our Lord, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.48. which is equally applicable to all Talents, as well of Riches as any other; <hi>For unto whomſoever much is given, of him ſhall much be required; and to whom men have Committed much, of him they will ask the more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. It would be a great, and worthy effect of a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and Univerſal Beneficence or Charity, in thoſe who have wealth, and power, and credit among us, to uſe all the intereſt they can make in procuring a publick National Eſtabliſhment of a truly Honourable Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of men, who ſhould make it their buſineſs, out of love to God, and Compaſſion towards their Brethren, to know among them all, the number and condition in all particulars, of all the poor in this Kingdom, and eſpecially in and about this great City: That ſo all thoſe who are able, might be forced to maintain them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by their own labour; and both thoſe whoſe la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour is not able to provide enough for their great charge, and thoſe who are unfit for any work at all, (which will be but few,) may be ſufficiently and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently provided for, and maintain'd as Sons of the ſame Father, and Brethren of our common Lord and Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt. If it were ſeriouſly conſidered and laid to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:64900:14"/>heart how many are ſtarv'd every year in their own houſes, and ſome too in the ſtreets, with hunger, or cold, or want of neceſſaries in one kind or other, (which amount to ſome hundreds in and about this City ſome years, as I have heard from thoſe who have reaſon to know) we ſhould look upon this as ſuch a Diſgrace and Contradiction to our Religion, which is the Law of Love, and the higheſt obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereto on ſo many accounts; and withal ſo great a guilt upon all who had, or might have power to reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy it, (if not on the whole Nation) that every Man would do his beſt to promote ſuch a brave deſign; without which 'tis very hard, if at all poſſible, that ſo Crying a Sin, and ſo Culpable a Neglect, which muſt lay ſome where, ſhould be wholly and effectually pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented.</p>
            <p>Now that ſuch wiſe and good men among us as have Eſtates, and Souls large enough to extend their Charitable Proviſion for the Poor to all after Ages, and deſire to do good with their wealth as long as the world ſhall laſt, may have encouragement from the ſucceſsful, as well as Pious Examples of their Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours, I ſhall read to you (as the Cuſtom is) the following account of the upright and prudent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of all thoſe publick foundations which are under the care and Government of the Lord Mayor, Commonalty, and Citizens of this Great and Ancient City for the year laſt paſt.</p>
            <div type="report">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:64900:14"/>
               <head>A True Report of the great Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Poor Children, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FRom which Report I ſhall obſerve theſe Two Things only.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> That Chriſt's Hoſpital was not in conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to receive any one Child this laſt year into their Houſe; partly, by reaſon of thoſe great Debts they ſtill labour under; and partly, by reaſon of their having taken in ſo many the year before that.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> That the Governours of <hi>St. Thomas Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpital,</hi> notwithſtanding their preſent neceſſary, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry chargeable Expence in Building, have not one bed leſs in that houſe, than were before; nor have deny'd any one Perſon who came for Cure, when there was a Vacancy; And that the Number of thoſe who have been there Cured this year laſt paſt exceeds that of any former year whatever.</item>
               </list>
               <p>So that Generous and well-diſpoſed minds, have here alſo, as well as among thoſe great numbers of Poor, who ſtand in need of preſent relief, fit objects for a Magnificent and Over flowing Bounty.</p>
               <p>To Conclude all; Let every one of us in the fear of God, and as we tender the welfare of our own Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Souls, take due care to be rightly informed of the neceſſity of this Great and Fundamental Duty, and the indiſpenſable obligation we have thereto, in our meaſure and capacity. Let us frequently reflect upon our own Conduct, and conſider how we ſhall be able to Anſwer our Judge when he ſhall proceed to give Sentence upon us, according to our demeanour in
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:64900:15"/>relation to his diſtreſſed Members: And in order here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, let us deeply fix, and often revolve in our minds theſe Avowed Maximes of Right Reaſon, and our Holy Religion, as ſo many irreſiſtible motives to do good, and to Communicate.</p>
               <p>That the time we have to ſpend in this World is but a Moment, an indiviſible Point, and next to No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, in proportion to that Eternity we are all made for, and are haſtning to apace. That conſequently here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, 'tis the firſt, and moſt pernicious Error, (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) that which leads to all the miſtakes and ſins Men commit here, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That they look upon this ſhort ſpan of Frail Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Life, (which is but their firſt ſtep and entrance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to being) as their All, that for which they were whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made, and ſo their Great and Only Concern, Affair, and Buſineſs; and do live, and govern themſelves, by this moſt falſe and moſt deſtructive Principle.</p>
               <p>Whereas the Main thing Chriſt teaches us, is to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage this preſent Life only in order to the next; and to eſteem nothing to be of any great conſequence to us, but what may ſecure and promote our Happineſs in that endleſs State which is before us; and to look upon all things, as mean, low, and ſcarce worth our Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which have no tendency to this our Maſter-deſign, <hi>viz.</hi> To be for ever Happy in the preſence and enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that Sovereign Good, for which we were made. That every Man is truly Valuable, only as God Values him. <hi>Tantus eſt quiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> quantus apud Deum.</hi> That he only is Great indeed, who is Great in the ſight of the Lord, <hi>Luk</hi> 1.15. who is Holy and Pious, Juſt and Merciful, who Loves and Honours God above all things, and makes his Will and Law the Rule of his Life and Actions.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:64900:15"/>
               <p>That nothing is more Reaſonable in it ſelf, nothing more agreeable to Humane Nature, (whence Humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which imports all obliging kindneſs, hath its Name) than that we ſhould aſſiſt and relieve others, made in the ſame Image, and after the ſame Likeneſs of God, our common Father; and who are of his Family and Houſhold, and his Children, as well as we are, with that overplus which God beſtows upon us for this very end.</p>
               <p>That if we do not this in a good proportion to our A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities, we are unfaithful Stewards of our Lords Eſtate; and it will fare accordingly with us at that great and univerſal Audit.</p>
               <p>That this Duty of Brotherly Love and Beneficence, is more earneſtly commanded, and more frequently inſiſted upon in the H. Scriptures than any other.</p>
               <p>That it is the moſt natural and irrefragable Proof of our Love to God, and our Gratitude to our Lord and Saviour Chriſt; and a peculiar Mark of our Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to Eternal Life, and of our being Gods Children indeed, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.12.</p>
               <p>That want of Bowels of Compaſſion to our needy Brother, is a demonſtration, That the love of God dwells not in us, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.17. And conſequently, that all pretence to Religion and Piety, is Vain, Falſe and Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocritical, without a competent Love to, and Practiſe of this Grace and Virtue, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.27.</p>
               <p>That doing a great deal of good to others, is the nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt approach which we can make to the Divine Nature, and Gods imitable perfections; whom we do herein chiefly reſemble.</p>
               <p>That it is only ſuch an outragious, criminal love of the World, as is wholly incompetible with the love of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:64900:16"/>God, which makes Rich Men ſuch ſlaves to their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney; or to ſuch fancy'd neceſſities of maintaining their Port, and outward State and Quality at ſuch an height, and ſo much to the prejudice of the Poor, that they are able to return to God, by his Receivers, ſo little of what he hath entruſted them with: But our Lord gives us no reaſon to believe, that ſuch vain ill founded Pleas will avail men any thing at his juſt Tribunal.</p>
               <p>They are only thoſe inordinate deſires, and undue gratifications of the ſenſes of the Body, or vices of the Mind, <hi>viz.</hi> Pride, Ambition, Covetouſneſs, which exhauſt that Treaſure that ſhould be lay'd up in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <hi>i. e.</hi> layd out in Works of Piety, and Mercy. So that in Concluſion, nothing but Brutiſh ſtupidity, or ſenſuality; or the improvident thoughtfulneſs of a Child, or of an Ideot; or the Pride or Malignity of an Apoſtate Spirit, can wholly extinguiſh the care, and deſtroy the practice of Beneficence and Charity. For the poor Covetous wretch is a proud of his large ſcope of Ground, or his great Heap of Gold, as the Haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Inſolent, Ambitious Man is of his Place or Title, (which perhaps his Wealth purchaſed him, or his Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor) or the Prodigal is, of his intemperate Luxurious Feaſts; or the Vain, Empty and Gay Man is, of the Fine Shew &amp; Figure he thinks he makes in Dreſs or Equipage. 'Tis only, I ſay, that Spirit and Air of the World which Chriſtianity obliges us to Mortify; that World, to which we ought to be Crucified, or Dead to, which drowns its Children in fooliſh and hurtful Luſts, in forgetful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God, of themſelves, and of their Neceſſitous Brethren; and afterwards, through groſs neglect of this Duty, in final perdition and deſtruction.</p>
               <p>That Alms-giving, is Trading with Heaven; that 'tis the higheſt improvement, and beſt advantage Rich
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:64900:16"/>Men can poſſibly make of their Wealth; and withal a ſure way never to loſe any part of it. This is the nature of Riches, ſaith St. <hi>Baſil,</hi> that if you give it liberally to the indigent, you have it ſtill; 'tis your own for ever: If you keep it all to your ſelf, you have it not; to be ſure you cannot have it long, and you will for every repent that you had it at all. Charity alone can turn this Fading, Periſhing Wealth into the true Riches; it will entitle us to all thoſe Favours and Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces God here beſtows upon his deareſt Children, and to that Everlaſting Happineſs which he reſerves for their Portion in the next World. Since Chriſt owns what is done to his poor Brethren, as done to Himſelf, and will accordingly Reward it in His Heavenly King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
               <p>And that Chriſt will at the laſt day (of which we cannot be too often reminded) have ſuch an eſpecial particular regard to this moſt important Duty; and will proceed upon it as one, if not the Main Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, of his enquiry into our Lives; and that our Final Doom, our Happy or Miſerable Eſtate to all Eternity, will in ſo very great meaſure depend, and turn upon the account we ſhall be able to give of our ſelves with relation hereto.</p>
               <p>In a word, Let us conſider ſeriouſly and often, that Beneficence and Charity, is the moſt Natural and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable; The moſt Commanded; The moſt Indiſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; The moſt Noble; The moſt Delightful; The moſt Advantageous; The moſt Chriſtian: Nay, the moſt Divine and God like Grace and Virtue.</p>
               <p>And let us all from the Cogency of ſo many Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, out of Love to our Good God, and our Lord, and Saviour Chriſt; to our Neighbours, and to our own Immortal Souls, ſo make it our Care and Study, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:64900:17"/>Buſineſs, to Aſſiſt and Comfort, and Relieve our Bleſſed Lord in thoſe Poor Needy Perſons, who are both his, and our Brethren; that we alſo may with them be made Heirs of that Kingdom God hath prepared for all His Children, for all truly Pious, all truly Charitable and Merciful Men.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To which, God of his Mercy bring us all, thro' Jeſus Chriſt our Lord; To whom,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:64900:17"/>
            <head>BOOKS Printed for <hi>B. Aylmer.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Forty Two Sermons and Diſcourſes upon ſeveral occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, moſt at Court; in Four Volumes, 8 <hi>vo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Rule of Faith: Or an Anſwer to the Treatiſe of Mr. <hi>J. Sergeant,</hi> 8 <hi>vo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Six Sermons concerning the Divinity and Incarnation of our Bleſſed Saviour: Of the Sacrifice &amp; Satisfaction of Chriſt; and of the Unity of the Divine Nature and the Bleſſed Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; againſt the <hi>Socinians,</hi> 8 <hi>vo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Six Sermons (newly Printed): One concerning Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Stedfaſtneſs in Religion; One of Family-Religion; Three of Education of Children; and One of the Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages of an Early Piety, in 8 <hi>vo.</hi> price 3 <hi>s.</hi> and alſo in 120. price bound. 18 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Perſwaſive to frequent Communion in the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, 8 <hi>vo.</hi> alone Stitcht price 3 <hi>d.</hi> or in 120. bound, price 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Diſcourſe againſt Tranſubſtantiation, 8 <hi>vo.</hi> alone Stitcht price 3 <hi>d.</hi> All Publiſhed by his Grace, <hi>John</hi> Lord Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Works of the Learned Dr. <hi>Iſaac Barrow,</hi> late Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of <hi>Trinity</hi> College in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and Publiſhed by his Grace, <hi>John</hi> Lord Arch Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury;</hi> in Four Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes in Folio.</p>
            <p>A Demonſtration of the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> in which the Truth of the Chriſtian Religion is proved, eſpecially againſt the <hi>Jews.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Charge of <hi>Richard</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Wells,</hi> to the Clergy of his Dioceſs.</p>
            <p>A Sermon preached before the Lord Mayor on Eaſter-Tueſday, on <hi>April</hi> the 21. being a Spittle-Sermon. As al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo Three ſingle Sermons on ſeveral occaſions. Writ by <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Wells.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:64900:18"/>
            <p>A Diſcourſe of the great Diſingenuity and Unreaſonable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Repining at Afflicting Providences; and of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence which they ought to have upon us: On <hi>Job.</hi> 2.10. Publiſhed upon occaſion of the Death of our Gracious So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign, Queen <hi>MARY,</hi> of moſt Bleſſed Memory; with a Preface containing ſome Obſervations touching Her Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Endowments, and Exemplary Life.</p>
            <p>Certain Propoſitions by which the Doctrine of the Holy <hi>Trinity</hi> is ſo explained, according to the Ancient Fathers, as to ſpeak it not Contradictory to Natural Reaſon: To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with a Defence of them, in Anſwer to the Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of a <hi>Socinian</hi> Writer, in his newly Printed Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions on the Explications of the Doctrine of the <hi>Trinity;</hi> Occaſioned by theſe Propoſitions among other Diſcourſes.</p>
            <p>A Sermon Preached before the Lord Mayor, on Eaſter-Wedneſday. As alſo Three ſingle Sermons on ſeveral oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions: Writ by <hi>Edward</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Glouceſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Holy Bible, containing the Old Teſtament, and the New, with Annotations and Parallel Scriptures; to which is Annexed the Harmony of the Goſpels: As alſo the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Weights, Coins and Meaſures, to our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Standard, and a Table of the Promiſes in Scripture; by <hi>Samuel Clark;</hi> Printed in Folio of a very Fair Letter, the like never before, in one Volume.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:64900:18"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
